<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % sharedents SYSTEM "shared-entities.xml" >
%sharedents;
]>

<chapter id="imagetransfer-specs">
  <info>
    <author>
      <firstname>Owen</firstname>
      <surname>Synge</surname>
    </author>
  </info>
  <title>Image transfer Specifications</title>
  <section id="imagetransfer-specs-intro">
    <para>The work flow is based on the concept of &vmil; which have a lifecycle. 
    All &vmil; have a URI and a UUID, a creation and expiry date and Version number. 
    If &vmil; change either UUID or URI they are considered different &vmil;, 
    and when a &vmil; is updated it is expected that the creation data is updated 
    and best to update the version number. It is recommended that the expiry data of an 
    &vmil; is 1 month from the creation date.</para>
    <para>Endorsers provide signed &vmil;, and accept the security responsibilities 
    of producing images as stated in the Image trust section of thsi document. 
    Subscribers use &vmil; and run them confident they can identify the endorser, and 
    decide if they will run the endorsers images.</para>
    <para>&vmil; can be valid or invalid from the perspective of the subscriber. 
    Valid &vmil; are signed, with a valid certificate from a CA trusted by the 
    subscriber, the current time is between the created and expiry date, and endorsers 
    subject in the &vmil; that matches the endorser, and the current version number 
    is greater or equal to the previous version number. If &vmil; do not match any 
    of these conditions the &vmil; is invalid. Subscribed &vmil; are referenced 
    by their UUID.</para>
    <para>The workflow also has the concept of image life cycles, which are related to image 
    list life cycles. An image maybe available or unavailable, created, and updated. From 
    the subscribers perspective available images cannot exist without a valid &vmil;
    that includes them. Images are secured with a sha512 value in the &vmil; that 
    matches the image.</para>
    <para>An image is identified by its UUID and its version number. Its current state 
    is defined by its presence or absence in a valid &vmil;. Valid images always have 
    greater or equal version numbers than previous versions.</para>
    <para>UUID's of &vmil; cannot overlap, and in the same way the UUID's of images cannot 
    overlap. It is considered a hostile action if UUID uniqueness is violated by an endorser. 
    Since &vmil; UUID's are only added or removed by the subscriber displaying errors and 
    rejecting &vmil; with clashing UUID's with the subscribers tools is enough to alert the 
    subscriber to such endorser actions. If two &vmil; provide images with the same UUID, 
    the image from the second &vmil; will be ignored and an error should be shown by the 
    subscribers tools.</para>
    <para>Updated &vmil; may contain new images referenced by new UUID's. These new 
    images will be ignored and WARNINGS shown until the &vmil; is re-subscribed. This 
    behavior keeps the subscriber in control of the Image UUID's and thier association to 
    &vmil; UUID's. It is always well defined which image belongs to which &vmil;
    and so the subscriber always knows the publisher of an image.</para>
    <para>Images UUID's no longer present in an &vmil; are no longer endorsed by the 
    endorser and so the images are no longer available, and consequently such images are 
    marked as "expired" an event is sent.</para>
    <para>The subscriber is aware of the complete history of an image through the meta 
    data of that image within the subscription tools, the date of expiry and renewal for 
    each state change for an image in an &vmil;.</para>
  </section>
</chapter> 

