<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                      "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % sharedents SYSTEM "shared-entities.xml" >
%sharedents;
]>

<section>
  <title>vmlisub</title>
  <para>This virtual maschine image list subscriber implementation is intended to be a production grade referance implementation.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>This application allows users to subscribe to virtual machine image lists, cache
the images referenced to in the image list, validate the images list with x509 
based public key cryptography, and validate the images against sha512 hashes in 
the images lists and provide events for further applications to process updates 
or expiries of virtual machine images without having to further validate the 
images. This set of applications are designed to provide a similar work flow
from each area of control to the imagelist archive.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>vmlisub_endorser - Endorsers of imagelist subscriptions.</listitem>
      <listitem>vmlisub_sub      - Subscription list details.</listitem>
      <listitem>vmlisub_image    - Image details.</listitem>
      <listitem>vmlisub_cache    - Cache images and update events.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>They work in conjunction with a database to ease navigation, a local cache of
image list subscriptions. The database is message format agnostic, but it
authenticates and validates all messages in import. Because these are just
caches of imagelists they are meant to be used the majority of the time without
intervention.</para>
    <para>If you are signing a list using the hepix image list signer, you should also
install this application and subscribe to your current image.</para>
    <para>It is intended to with a couple of cron scripts to be informed at any time if
your local images are matching signatures in the image list.</para>
    <para>Anyone curious about this application should consider this application a
software application similar to Debian's 'aptitude' or Redhats 'yum', but rather
for virtual machines, authenticated by the x509 signatures.</para>

  </section>
  <section>
    <title>vmlisub_endorser</title>
    <para>This application is for managing who the subscriber trusts to update image 
lists. Since individuals are identified with x509 certificates, Each certificate
has an issuing certificate and a unique string called a 'subject' to identify 
the certificate. The 'subject' of a certificate and the 'subject' of the issuing 
certificate combined are called 'credentials', and will be globally unique.</para>

  </section>
</section>
