<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % sharedents SYSTEM "shared-entities.xml" >
%sharedents;
]>
<chapter id="organisation-intro">
  <info>
    <author>
      <firstname>Owen</firstname>
      <surname>Synge</surname>
    </author>
  </info>
  <title>Organisation Introduction</title>
  <section id="organisation-intro-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Virtaulisation can potentially allow experiments to deploy the same &vee; across multiple sites, 
    which will greatly benefit experiments in a consistent run time environment. This brings new 
    challenges as sites have always been responsible for all security issues relating to their computing 
    resources but with the introduction &vee; being presented to experiments site security can no longer be 
    the sole responsibility of the site running a job.</para>

    <para>Several &hep; pilot projects have already shown that CPU intensive tasks could easily run on a cloud 
    infrastructure. Sites within the &vwg; use &opennebula;, &nimbus;, &eucalyptus; and some are evaluating 
    &openstack;.</para>
    
    <para>The &hep; community have long used batch computing models to maximise computing efficiency, this 
    allows jobs to be queued so that each compute node is always occupied. &hep; sites have typically 
    optimised their batch queues so that different user communities can benefit from under utilised resources 
    from other user groups, while retaining a quota of CPU usage proportional to their budget, so called 
    &fss;. It was noted that &hep; users on Clouds typically installed batch queues to maximise their job 
    efficiency but since resources where tied to a single customer it is not possible to use &fss;.</para>
    
  </section>
  <section id="organisation-intro-scope">
    <title>Scope</title>
    <para>The &vwg; main focus is to provide sites a way to control and mange &vmi;es provided by 
    experiments, and run them in trusted environments with in the current computing environment provided 
    under Grid computing.</para>
    <para>With such a diversity of cloud solutions all under going very active development it is 
    impossible for a group such as &vwg; to only support a single cloud implementation, as we would not be 
    serving the needs to our community.</para>
    <para>Since &hep; is very concerned with job efficiency and has been well served by the batch queue model 
    of computing it was seen that the &vwg; cannot limit their effort to only working with cloud based solutions 
    and our work scope should be equally applicable to Cloud and &vee; on a batch queue compute node.</para>
    <para>One of the side effects of &hep; having pioneered Grid computing, is that the community have already 
    learnt about the diversity of sites, and considerable effort has been put into minimising the differences 
    between sites from a customer perspective. The &hep; community and sites serving them have come to understand 
    that some areas of site management are not practical to unify. In areas where tools and practices are 
    developing quickly innovating is potentially hindered by enforcing standardisation. This is also true of 
    areas where considerable effort has been invested, and change would be detrimental, a good example of this 
    is in site deployment and configuration. The &vwg; decided very early on that we where not going to look 
    into areas that would effect sites local deployment and configuration. The rational was that many sites 
    already had virtulisation strategies, and sites that did not, should not be prevented from working with newer 
    tools and cloud infrastructures.</para>
  </section> 
    
</chapter>
